# 李锦超

inchaoli.com

**∠** jcli@se.cuhk.edu.hk

**3** +86-17721500797





#### ■ 个人简介

本人是香港中文大学人机交互实验室的博士生,导师是蒙美玲教授。在此之前,我在卢晶教授的指导下获得了2019年南京大学声学专业学士学位。我的研究方向主要为人工智能在语音、语言和健康中的应用,研究的课题主要包括认知障碍和精神疾病的诊断和筛查、多模态情感识别等。

# ♥ 研究兴趣

- 人工智能在语音、语言和健康中的应用
- 多模态机器学习:不同数据的表征和融合
- 迁移学习: 多语种或低资源数据的领域自适应和泛化
- 强化学习:面向任务的对话策略学习

# 血 教育经历

博士 | 香港中文大学 信息科学@系统工程与工程管理系,导师:蒙美玲教授

📋 2019年8月-2023年7月(预期)

₹ 香港

• 学士 | 南京大学

声学@物理(主修)和电子信息(辅修)学院,导师:卢晶教授

📋 2015年9月-2019年6月

← 南京

### ■ 发表论文[更多]

- 李锦超等,"基于层级链式框架的情绪发声识别", IEEE ICASSP, 2023. 🚨 🖟
- 李锦超等, "基于任务相关特征的阿尔兹海默症检测", IEEE ICASSP, 2023. 🚨
- 李锦超等,"阿尔茨海默病检测中声学预训练表示的比较研究", CCF NCMMSC, 2022. [2]
- · 李锦超等, "基于上下文的多模态情感识别", ICSA INTERSPEECH, 2022. ☑ Д
- 李锦超等, "阿尔兹海默症检测的语音和语言特征的比较研究", IEEE ICASSP, 2021. 🚨 🚨 🖟
- 李锦超、朱长宝,"基于传声器阵列确定声源信息的方法、装置及电子设备",专利: CN110148422B, 2021. □ 🚨
- 李锦超、周靖妍, "面向任务的对话系统策略学习", IERG6130课程报告, 2020. 🚨

### ₩ 科研经历

基于语音和语言的表征、多模态、多语种认知障碍检测,利用降维、迁移学习等方法解决低资源、多样化问题。

• The ACII Affective Vocal Bursts (A-VB)竞赛 | Hume AI □ 2022年7月-2022年9月 利用标签关系的多任务、多文化高维情感识别。在TWO, HIGH和CULTURE赛道上分别相对超过最高基线35%(冠军)、27%(第二)和37%(冠军)。(相似赛事在ICML、ACII、CVPR均有举办。)

• 情感识别、语音增强 | 腾讯 □ 2021年10月-2022年4月

导师:王帅博士@腾讯光子X-data研究组 利用上下文信息和多模态注意力机制进行情感识别;利用频谱信息进行ASR适配的实时单通道语音增强。

• 声源计数 | 地平线机器人 □ 2018年12月-2019年4月

利用盲源分离前后信息辅助判断混响、带噪情况下双通道声源数目的正定情况。(南京大学优秀毕业论文)

#### ♀ 荣誉奖项

• ACII A-VB学术竞赛 (两赛道冠军&一赛道亚军)

**2**022

• 南京大学优秀毕业论文

**1** 2019

🥊 深圳

• 全国/美国大学生数学建模竞赛(二等奖/M奖)

**2017&2018** 

• 教育部国家奖学金

□ 2017

# ♥ 专业技能

语言:中文(母语)、英语(熟练)

编程: Python (熟练)、MATLAB (熟练)

# JINCHAO LI

jinchaoli.com
jinchaoli.com

jcli@se.cuhk.edu.hk

**>** +86-17721500797

JinchaoLove



### **■ SHORT BIO**

Jinchao Li is a Ph.D. candidate at Human-Computer Communications Laboratory (HCCL) in CUHK, advised by Prof. Helen Meng. He obtained a B.S. in Acoustics from Nanjing University in 2019, advised by Prof. Jing Lu. His research aims at human-centred AI for speech, language, and healthcare, such as speech-based Neurocognitive or mental disorder recognition.

### RESEARCH INTERESTS

- · Human-centred AI for speech, language and healthcare
- · Multimodal machine learning: representation and fusion of heterogeneous data
- · Transfer learning: domain adaptation and generalization for multilingual or low-resource data
- Reinforcement learning: task-oriented dialogue systems

### **EDUCATION**

• Ph.D. | The Chinese University of Hong Kong Information Science @SEEM, advised by Prof. Helen Meng **\text{\text{d}}** Aug. 2019 – Jul. 2023 (expected)

Hong Kong

Nanjing

• B.S. | Nanjing University

Sep. 2015 – Jun. 2019

Acoustics @Physics (major) & EE (minor), advised by Prof. Jing Lu

# SELECTED PUBLICATIONS [MORE]

- Jinchao Li, et al. "A Hierarchical Regression Chain Framework for Affective Vocal Burst Recognition." ICASSP'23.
- Jinchao Li, et al. "Leveraging Pretrained Representations with Task-related Keywords for Alzheimer's Disease Detection." ICASSP'23.
- Jinchao Li, et al. "Alzheimer's Disease Detection using Pretrained Acoustic Representations: A Comparison Study." NCMMSC'22.
- Jinchao Li, et al. "Context-aware Multimodal Fusion for Emotion Recognition." INTERSPEECH'22. 🚨 🔼
- Jinchao Li, et al. "A Comparative Study of Acoustic and Linguistic Features Classification for Alzheimer's Disease Detection." ICASSP'21. 🔁 🛕
- Jinchao Li, Changbao Zhu. "Method, Device and Electronic Equipment for Determining Sound Source Information." Patent: CN110148422B, 2021.
- Jinchao Li, et al. "Policy Learning for Task-oriented Dialogue Systems", IERG6130 Project Report, 2020. 🖪

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

• Neurocognitive Disorder Detection | HCCL & Microsoft Research Asia Jun. 2020/2022 - Present Advised by Prof. Helen Meng @HCCL-CUHK & Dr. Dongsheng Li and Kaitao Song @MSR Asia Hong Kong, Shanghai Feature engineering, multimodal fusion and multilingual generalization for speech-based disease detection, solving data scarcity and diversity problems.

• The ACII Affective Vocal Bursts (A-VB) Competition | Hume AI

**J**ul. 2022 – Sep. 2022

Multi-culture affect recognition by modeling label dependency. (Similar competitions have been held in ICML, ACII, and CVPR.)

• Emotion Recognition (ER), Speech Enhancement (SE) | Tencent

Oct. 2021 – May 2022

Advised by Dr. Shuai Wang @Tencent Lightspeed & Quantum Studios Multimodal ER using context information and attention mechanism, adjust waveform-based SE for ASR. Shenzhen

• Source Counting (SC) | Horizon Robotics

Dec. 2018 – Apr. 2019

Advised by Prof. Jing Lu @NJU and Mr. Changbao Zhu @Horizon Robotics

Nanjing

Binaural speech SC in reverberated and noisy scenarios with independent component analysis. (Excellent Undergraduate Thesis)

### **Q** HONORS & AWARDS

• The ACII A-VB Competition (Winners in two tracks, Sencond in one track)

**2022** 2019

· Excellent Undergraduate Thesis, Nanjing University

• Meritorious Winner Prize in National/American Mathematical Contest in Modeling

**2017&2018** 

· National Scholarship, the Ministry of Education in China

2017

### SKILLS